<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Collectivism | OLES</title>
    <link>www.oles.cl/tag/collectivism/</link>
      <atom:link href="www.oles.cl/tag/collectivism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Collectivism</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>es-cl</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/www.oles.cl/media/logo_hud5651eda9fc30916f5e80eead078350f_17375_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Collectivism</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/tag/collectivism/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Collection With Indigenous People: Fieldwork Experiences From Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At present, the Mapuche are the largest indigenous group living in Chile and, up until the present day, they are considered a disadvantaged group in Chilean society in terms of poverty, education and discrimination indicators. In recent decades, this group has been involved in a violent conflict with the Chilean state, forestry and hydroelectric industries and big landowners due mainly to territorial claims of the ancestral land that is currently inhabited and exploited by these different actors. In the present chapter, we narrate the process of data collection with indigenous participants within the framework of a three-year long project about representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between the Mapuche and the non-indigenous majority in Chile. We focus on the challenges that data collection involved by highlighting the process of participant recruitment and trust issues revolving around data collection, as well as retribution practices. Moreover, we also highlight the pros and cons of having non-indigenous Chilean and international researchers conducting fieldwork in this context. Another aspect we address is how methodological approaches may influence the data quality and participants’ degree of involvement with the project, by highlighting how these issues interconnect with cultural differences and this indigenous group’s worldview and cultural practices. We hope this chapter may provide significant insights on how to deal with some of the difficulties that data collection with indigenous people may involve.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Collectivism and Tightness Moderate Responses to Norm Violators: Effects on Power Perception, Moral Emotions, and Leader Support</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Responses to norm violators are poorly understood. On one hand, norm violators are perceived as powerful, which may help them to get ahead. On the other hand, norm violators evoke moral outrage, which may frustrate their upward social mobility. We addressed this paradox by considering the role of culture. Collectivistic cultures value group harmony and tight cultures value social order. We therefore hypothesized that collectivism and tightness moderate reactions to norm violators. We presented 2,369 participants in 19 countries with a norm violation or a norm adherence scenario. In individualistic cultures, norm violators were considered more powerful than norm abiders and evoked less moral outrage, whereas in collectivistic cultures, norm violators were considered less powerful and evoked more moral outrage. Moreover, respondents in tighter cultures expressed a stronger preference for norm followers as leaders. Cultural values thus influence responses to norm violators, which may have downstream consequences for violators’ hierarchical positions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between indigenous and non-indigenous people: The Mapuche in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between indigenous and non-indigenous people: The Mapuche in Chile&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
