<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ana Figueiredo | OLES</title>
    <link>www.oles.cl/author/ana-figueiredo/</link>
      <atom:link href="www.oles.cl/author/ana-figueiredo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ana Figueiredo</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>es-cl</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/www.oles.cl/author/ana-figueiredo/avatar_hufd5c2c7282ef485e5926d5652c6faccd_30101_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Ana Figueiredo</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/author/ana-figueiredo/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigadora Ana Figueiredo participa en Congreso de Psicología en Buenos Aires</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/post/2023-18-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0100</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/post/2023-18-12/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;SIMPOSIO| El pasado 1 de diciembre Ana Figueiredo, investigadora de OLES, participó en el XV Congreso internacional de Investigación y Práctica Profesional en Psicología, organizado por la Universidad de Buenos Aires. En este contexto, Ana expuso su trabajo en el simposio internacional Memoria Colectiva e Identidad Social, el cual tiene por titulo “Las conexiones entre ideologías postcoloniales y las demandas de reparación y reconocimiento hacia el pueblo Mapuche”. Este consistió en un estudio cualitativo con 29 personas Mapuche, donde se trabajaron distintas ideologías postcoloniales y la manera en que son percibidas las demandas de reparación y reconocimiento del pueblo Mapuche en la actualidad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¡Revisa el simposio en el siguiente link!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BPiHYwFGpWk&amp;amp;t=3685s&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BPiHYwFGpWk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigadoras OLES presentan ponencias en Congresos internacionales ISPP &amp; ISA</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/post/2023-08-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/post/2023-08-01/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Durante el mes de julio, investigadoras e investigadores de OLES participaron de congresos internacionales para difundir sus hallazgos respecto a los estudios de legitimidad social y violencia que ha llevado a cabo nuestra organización.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El reciente día martes 11 de julio la directora de OLES, Mónica Gerber de la Facultad de Psicología de la Universidad Diego Portales, participó en la Conferencia Anual de la International Society of Political Psychology (ISPP) en Montreal, Canada. En esta instancia expuso la conferencia &lt;em&gt;“Justice and social change: the importance of procedural justice in shaping collective action”.&lt;/em&gt; Su presentación giró en torno a la pregunta ¿por qué las personas están dispuestas a participar en la acción colectiva y bajo que circunstancias la violencia se convierte en opción? Su propuesta se basó en un diálogo crítico con la psicología social de los movimientos sociales y la teoría de la justicia procedimental.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La investigadora de OLES Ana Figuereido también participó en esta Conferencia Anual. En esta instancia presentó “Postcolonial ideologies, reparation and recognition demands: The Mapuche in Chile”, la cual fue parte del simposio titulado Recognition, reparations, and resistance: Responses to colonialism and coloniality in the Americas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En el marco de esta conferencia internacional, Ana también participó como expositora y moderadora en el Summer Academy ISPP, donde presentó &lt;em&gt;“Doing research in postcolonial settings: Dealing with coloniality and sociohistorical phenomena in our research agendas”.&lt;/em&gt; Esta exposición tuvo como objetivo invitar a los y las estudiantes a reflexionar sobre la relevancia del de la colonialidad en las investigaciones en psicología política así como en las ciencias sociales contemporáneas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por último, durante la última semana de Junio se realizó el XX ISA World Congress of Sociology con sede en Melbourne, Australia. En esta instancia, Macarena Orchard, investigadora de OLES presentó, junto a Kathya Araujo, el trabajo “Beyond legitimacy. How to study authority in contemporary societies”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lanzamiento OLES</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/event/lanzamiento/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/event/lanzamiento/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;El 9 de septiembre será la inauguración de la página del &lt;strong&gt;Observatorio Violencia y Legitimidad Social&lt;/strong&gt; (OLES).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
ric industries and big landowners due mainly to territorial claims of the ancestral land that is currently inhabited and exploited by these different actors. In the present chapter, we narrate the process of data collection with indigenous participants within the framework of a three-year long project about representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between the Mapuche and the non-indigenous majority in Chile. We focus on the challenges that data collection involved by highlighting the process of participant recruitment and trust issues revolving around data collection, as well as retribution practices. Moreover, we also highlight the pros and cons of having non-indigenous Chilean and international researchers conducting fieldwork in this context. Another aspect we address is how methodological approaches may influence the data quality and participants’ degree of involvement with the project, by highlighting how these issues interconnect with cultural differences and this indigenous group’s worldview and cultural practices. We hope this chapter may provide significant insights on how to deal with some of the difficulties that data collection with indigenous people may involve.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Collectivism and Tightness Moderate Responses to Norm Violators: Effects on Power Perception, Moral Emotions, and Leader Support</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Responses to norm violators are poorly understood. On one hand, norm violators are perceived as powerful, which may help them to get ahead. On the other hand, norm violators evoke moral outrage, which may frustrate their upward social mobility. We addressed this paradox by considering the role of culture. Collectivistic cultures value group harmony and tight cultures value social order. We therefore hypothesized that collectivism and tightness moderate reactions to norm violators. We presented 2,369 participants in 19 countries with a norm violation or a norm adherence scenario. In individualistic cultures, norm violators were considered more powerful than norm abiders and evoked less moral outrage, whereas in collectivistic cultures, norm violators were considered less powerful and evoked more moral outrage. Moreover, respondents in tighter cultures expressed a stronger preference for norm followers as leaders. Cultural values thus influence responses to norm violators, which may have downstream consequences for violators’ hierarchical positions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between indigenous and non-indigenous people: The Mapuche in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between indigenous and non-indigenous people: The Mapuche in Chile&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracing Mapuche Exclusion from Post-Dictatorial Truth Commissions in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This article critically examines the official misrecognition of Mapuche experiences of violence during Augusto Pinochet’s dictatorship (1973–1990) in state-sponsored truth commissions in Chile. We examine official post-dictatorial truth commission politics, narratives and procedures, analyzing how they envisioned the Mapuche as a political (absent) subject and how specific and homogenizing notions of victimhood were produced. We draw attention to three forms of cultural response by the Mapuche toward the official practices of the truth commissions from a bottom-up perspective: indifference, ambivalence and cultural resistance. We then draw attention to unofficial initiatives by nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) and grassroots groups that have aimed to tackle this gap in the transitional justice mechanisms by creating oppositional knowledge. We see in these counter initiatives a valuable knowledge that could allow the creation of bridges between Mapuche communities, mechanisms of transitional justice, grassroots and NGO activism and the Chilean state.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Too long to compensate? Time perceptions, emotions, and compensation for colonial conflicts</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the present article we analyze the role of perceptions of time and ingroup-focused compunction and anger on the desire to compensate the outgroup in relation to historical colonial conflicts. Furthermore, we analyze the relationships between the aforementioned variables and perceptions of the past as being violent and perceptions that compensation has been enough. By means of multiple group structural equation modeling using 1 Portuguese sample (N = 170) and 1 Dutch sample (N = 238), we were able to show that perceptions of the time passed between the negative events and the present day are negatively related to compensatory behavioral intentions. Furthermore, the belief that past compensation has been enough is negatively related to ingroup-focused anger and compunction. Anger (Portuguese sample only) and compunction are positively associated with intentions of compensation. The implications of our results for the field of intergroup relations are discussed. (PsycINFO Database Record (c) 2016 APA, all rights reserved)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
