<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cristóbal Moya | OLES</title>
    <link>www.oles.cl/author/cristobal-moya/</link>
      <atom:link href="www.oles.cl/author/cristobal-moya/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Cristóbal Moya</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>es-cl</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/www.oles.cl/media/logo_hud5651eda9fc30916f5e80eead078350f_17375_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Cristóbal Moya</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/author/cristobal-moya/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it Worth the Risk? Grievances and Street Protest Participation During the COVID-19 Pandemic in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica10/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica10/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>¿ Qué hacer? Repertorios de accion frente a las injusticias percibidas en los lugares de trabajo en Santiago de Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica11/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Police violence as punishment: Does excessive use of force serve to punish those who threaten status and power hierarchies in society?</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/preprint-monica/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/preprint-monica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do some people view excessive police violence as acceptable? We reason that excessive police violence not only seeks to control crime, but also to punish criminal offenders. We propose the concept of police violence for punishment and explore its associations with different forms of punishment and punishment motivations. We reason that some people support excessive police violence to reinforce status and power hierarchies with minority groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We draw on data from a representative sample of adults living in Chile conducted in 2015 (n=1,302). We use structural equation models to predict support for police violence for punishment, legal and extra-legal violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Police violence for punishment was strongly related to support for extra-legal punishment. Punitive police violence and extra-legal punishment were both predicted by the motivation to restore status and power relationships, followed by deterrence. In contrast, norm restoration was the main predictor of legal punishment. Police violence for punishment was significantly less supported by ethnic minority members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that police excessive use of force can usefully be understood as police violence as punishment. We discuss the extent to which police repression is perceived to restore status and power hierarchies threatened by crime. We conclude that reducing police violence requires a political and cultural process well beyond reforming police protocols and procedures. Working towards more horizontal relations between police officers, citizens and minority groups should reduce perceived needs to restore power and status relationships, hereby reducing support for police violence as punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acting collectively to confront injustice</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica0/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the justification of intergroup violence: The roles of procedural justice, police legitimacy, and group identity in attitudes toward violence among indigenous people</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do people justify intergroup violence? We examine public attitudes toward violence perpetrated by indigenous activists to claim for rights and violence by police officers against indigenous people. We assess the roles that group identity, perceived police legitimacy, and procedurally just policing toward indigenous people play in the justification of intergroup violence among members of that minority group. Method: We present findings from 2 surveys (Study 1, n = 1,493; Study 2, n = 198) and an experiment (Study 3, n = 76) conducted among indigenous people in Chile. Studies 1 and 2 measure, and Study 3 manipulates, perceptions of police procedural justice toward indigenous people. Effects of procedural justice on police legitimacy (Studies 2 and 3) and attitudes toward violence for social change and social control (Studies 1–3) are analyzed. Result: Higher perceptions of procedurally just policing toward indigenous people predict higher support for police violence and lower support for violence perpetrated by indigenous activists. These effects are mediated by perceived police legitimacy and moderated by identification with the minority group. Among indigenous people who identify strongly with their group, perceiving high procedural justice predicts greater police legitimacy, greater support for police violence, and lesser support for violence perpetrated by indigenous activists. Conclusions: Findings contribute to an emerging literature on the roles of procedural justice and legitimacy in violence perceptions. They suggest that fair, respectful, and neutral treatment by police officers toward indigenous people may shape people’s views on the appropriateness of various forms of police and civic violence in a particular intergroup context. (PsycInfo Database Record (c) 2020 APA, all rights reserved)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
