<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jonathan Jackson | OLES</title>
    <link>www.oles.cl/author/jonathan-jackson/</link>
      <atom:link href="www.oles.cl/author/jonathan-jackson/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jonathan Jackson</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>es-cl</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/www.oles.cl/media/logo_hud5651eda9fc30916f5e80eead078350f_17375_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Jonathan Jackson</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/author/jonathan-jackson/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Police violence as punishment: Does excessive use of force serve to punish those who threaten status and power hierarchies in society?</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/preprint-monica/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/preprint-monica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do some people view excessive police violence as acceptable? We reason that excessive police violence not only seeks to control crime, but also to punish criminal offenders. We propose the concept of police violence for punishment and explore its associations with different forms of punishment and punishment motivations. We reason that some people support excessive police violence to reinforce status and power hierarchies with minority groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We draw on data from a representative sample of adults living in Chile conducted in 2015 (n=1,302). We use structural equation models to predict support for police violence for punishment, legal and extra-legal violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Police violence for punishment was strongly related to support for extra-legal punishment. Punitive police violence and extra-legal punishment were both predicted by the motivation to restore status and power relationships, followed by deterrence. In contrast, norm restoration was the main predictor of legal punishment. Police violence for punishment was significantly less supported by ethnic minority members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that police excessive use of force can usefully be understood as police violence as punishment. We discuss the extent to which police repression is perceived to restore status and power hierarchies threatened by crime. We conclude that reducing police violence requires a political and cultural process well beyond reforming police protocols and procedures. Working towards more horizontal relations between police officers, citizens and minority groups should reduce perceived needs to restore power and status relationships, hereby reducing support for police violence as punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the justification of intergroup violence: The roles of procedural justice, police legitimacy, and group identity in attitudes toward violence among indigenous people</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do people justify intergroup violence? We examine public attitudes toward violence perpetrated by indigenous activists to claim for rights and violence by police officers against indigenous people. We assess the roles that group identity, perceived police legitimacy, and procedurally just policing toward indigenous people play in the justification of intergroup violence among members of that minority group. Method: We present findings from 2 surveys (Study 1, n = 1,493; Study 2, n = 198) and an experiment (Study 3, n = 76) conducted among indigenous people in Chile. Studies 1 and 2 measure, and Study 3 manipulates, perceptions of police procedural justice toward indigenous people. Effects of procedural justice on police legitimacy (Studies 2 and 3) and attitudes toward violence for social change and social control (Studies 1–3) are analyzed. Result: Higher perceptions of procedurally just policing toward indigenous people predict higher support for police violence and lower support for violence perpetrated by indigenous activists. These effects are mediated by perceived police legitimacy and moderated by identification with the minority group. Among indigenous people who identify strongly with their group, perceiving high procedural justice predicts greater police legitimacy, greater support for police violence, and lesser support for violence perpetrated by indigenous activists. Conclusions: Findings contribute to an emerging literature on the roles of procedural justice and legitimacy in violence perceptions. They suggest that fair, respectful, and neutral treatment by police officers toward indigenous people may shape people’s views on the appropriateness of various forms of police and civic violence in a particular intergroup context. (PsycInfo Database Record (c) 2020 APA, all rights reserved)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Justifying violence: legitimacy, ideology and public support for police use of force</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under what conditions do people support police use of force? In this paper we assess some of the empirical links between police legitimacy, political ideology (right-wing authoritarianism and social dominance orientation), and support for ‘reasonable’ use of force (e.g. an officer striking a citizen in self-defence) and ‘excessive’ use of force (e.g. an officer using violence to arrest an unarmed person who is not offering violent resistance). Analysing data from an online survey with US participants (n = 186) we find that legitimacy is a positive predictor of reasonable but not excessive police use of force, and that political ideology predicts support for excessive but not reasonable use of force. We conclude with the idea that legitimacy places normative constraints around police power. On the one hand, legitimacy is associated with increased support for the use of force, but only when violence is bounded within certain acceptable limits. On the other hand, excessive use of force seems to require an extra-legal justification that is – at least in our analysis – partly ideological. Our findings open up a new direction of research in what is currently a rather sparse psychological literature on the ability of legitimacy to ‘tame’ coercive power.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Authority and Punishment: On the Ideological Basis of Punitive Attitudes towards Criminals</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three explanations dominate the literature as to why people support tough sentencing of criminal offenders. The first is an instrumental perspective: people are concerned about becoming a victim of crime and they look to punishment to reduce future harm. The second is a relational perspective: people are concerned about community breakdown, and they support punishment to restore moral boundaries. The third is a psychological model based on ideological preferences: people desire conformity and authority in society, and they look to institutions to punish transgressions that threaten collective security. Building on the work of Tyler and Boeckmann (1977), we show that right-wing authoritarianism predicts both the extent to which people worry about social threats and the extent to which they support harsh punitive measures. Bridging research from political psychology and criminology, we conclude with the idea that popular punitive sentiment is grounded in an uncritical submission to authorities, an adherence to conservative moral values, and consonant concerns about collective security and cohesion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retribution as Revenge and Retribution as Just Deserts</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica8/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public Opinion Towards the Lay Magistracy and the Sentencing Council Guidelines: The Effects of Information on Attitudes</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public opinion surveys have long documented public criticism of ‘lenient’ sentencers. There are two principal perceptions contributing to negative attitudes: a lack of community input and the view that sentencers determine sentence according to their own views. This study embeds an experimental design within a representative survey of respondents in England and Wales (n = 1,004), supplemented by laboratory-based work (n = 230) and focus groups. Results demonstrated that the public is ill-informed about both the magistracy and the sentencing guidelines. In addition, providing information about sentencing changed public attitudes to sentencing and reduced public punitiveness. Respondents were less critical of disposals and less punitive in their own sentence recommendations when they had been given context about the structure of sentencing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
