<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publicaciones | OLES</title>
    <link>www.oles.cl/publication/</link>
      <atom:link href="www.oles.cl/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publicaciones</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>es-cl</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/www.oles.cl/media/logo_hud5651eda9fc30916f5e80eead078350f_17375_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Publicaciones</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social contagion, violence, and suicide among adolescents</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica12/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legitimacy, Justice and Justification of Intergroup Violence between the Police and Protestors in Chile [Presentación]</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/paper_psykhe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/paper_psykhe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;El Observatorio de Violencia y legitimidad (OLES) presentó su paper de Psykhe en el &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.easp.eu/news/itm/call_for_papers__33rd_meeting_of-1456.html#:~:text=The%20meeting%20takes%20place%20in,%3A%20dealing%20with%20societal%20divides%E2%80%9D.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;33rd Meeting of the German Peace Psychology Forum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;descargar-la-presentaciónhttpsgithubcomoles-clolesrawmainassetsmediamarburg2022_gerberpptx&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oles-cl/oles/raw/main/assets/media/marburg2022_gerber.pptx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Descargar la presentación&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a puedes=&#34;&#34; descargar=&#34;&#34; el=&#34;&#34; programa=&#34;&#34; apretando=&#34;&#34; siguiente=&#34;&#34; botón=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/oles-cl/oles/raw/main/assets/media/marburg2022_gerber.pptx&#34; role=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lanzamiento sitio web y Encuesta Longitudinal [Presentación]</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/lanzamiento_oles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/lanzamiento_oles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;El Observatorio de Violencia y legitimidad (OLES), el 9 de septiembre de 2022, brindó el &lt;a href=&#34;https://oles-cl.netlify.app/event/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Seminario de prácticas investigativas&lt;/a&gt;, con la presentación del sitio web y los resultados de la Encuesta Longitudinal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;descargar-la-presentación-en-pdfhttpsgithubcomoles-clolesrawmainassetsmedialanzamiento_oles2022pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oles-cl/oles/raw/main/assets/media/lanzamiento_oles2022.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Descargar la presentación en pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a puedes=&#34;&#34; descargar=&#34;&#34; el=&#34;&#34; programa=&#34;&#34; apretando=&#34;&#34; siguiente=&#34;&#34; botón=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary&#34; href=&#34;https://github.com/oles-cl/oles/raw/main/assets/media/lanzamiento_oles2022.pdf&#34; role=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;video-de-la-presentación&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Video de la presentación&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recuerden que el &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/DPqTKYSvh30&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;video de la presentación&lt;/a&gt; y futuros seminarios podrán encontrarlos en el &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCpzqa_c3Okvx3Ikv3t2Ld2Q&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;canal de youtube de OLES&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&#34;embed-responsive-item&#34; src=&#34;https://youtu.be/DPqTKYSvh30&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it Worth the Risk? Grievances and Street Protest Participation During the COVID-19 Pandemic in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica10/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica10/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>¿ Qué hacer? Repertorios de accion frente a las injusticias percibidas en los lugares de trabajo en Santiago de Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica11/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homosexuality Justification and Social Distance. A Cross-Cultural Approach from Latin America Using World Values Survey Data</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20223/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20223/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>System Justification or Social Dominance? A Multilevel Test of the Ideological Motivators of Perceived Discrimination</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20221/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20221/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Political Psychology of Inequality. Why Rising Rates of Inequality Matter for Democracy</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20222/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20222/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attitudes Toward Punishment</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Justificación de los chilenos al uso de tácticas violentas ejercidas por manifestantes de Primera Línea en Chile.</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/vz_maria_teresa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/vz_maria_teresa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;El  objetivo  de  esta  tesis  fue  evaluar  el  efecto  de  identificación  grupal,  eficacia percibida del uso de las tácticas violentas y las emociones grupales de los chilenos en  la  justificación  que  estos  realizan  del  uso  de  tácticas  violentas  ejercidas  por manifestantes  de  primera  línea  en  la  protesta  social en  Chile.    Al  no  encontrar modelos explicativos para esta temática se realizó una aproximación teórica desde la psicología social, en especial desde la teórica de la acción colectiva en base a los modelos SIMCA y EMSICA, que fueron utilizados como referentes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metodológicamente se usaron los datos la primera ola de la encuesta Legitimidad de  Carabineros:  violencia,  derechos  humanos  y  control  social  y  contempló  una 
muestra no probabilista  por cuotas  de 2.505 casos. Como técnicas de análisis se utilizaron técnicas multivariantes: Análisis Factorial y Análisis de Ecuaciones 
Estructurales.  El  principal  hallazgo  es  que  identificación  con  manifestantes  de primera línea (identificación grupal), eficacia percibida del uso de tácticas violentas (eficacia percibida), emociones negativas hacia Carabineros y emociones positivas hacia manifestantes de primera línea (emociones grupales) tienen un efecto en la justificación  del  uso  de  tácticas  violentas  ejercidas  por  manifestantes  de  primera línea en la protesta. En base a los datos trabajados, el modelo que tiene un mejor ajuste explicativo para la muestra analizadas es el que plantea que la identificación con manifestantes de primera línea tiene un efecto mediador sobre la justificación de tácticas violentas en la protesta. En este caso la identificación con manifestantes encapsula  elementos  (efectos)  de  eficacia  percibida  del  uso  de  la  violencia  en  la protesta y emociones positivas hacia manifestantes de primera línea, pero, además, considera que existe un efecto directo de estas variables en la justificación  de los chilenos del uso de tácticas violentas ejercida por manifestantes de primera línea en la protesta en Chile.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Police violence as punishment: Does excessive use of force serve to punish those who threaten status and power hierarchies in society?</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/preprint-monica/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/preprint-monica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do some people view excessive police violence as acceptable? We reason that excessive police violence not only seeks to control crime, but also to punish criminal offenders. We propose the concept of police violence for punishment and explore its associations with different forms of punishment and punishment motivations. We reason that some people support excessive police violence to reinforce status and power hierarchies with minority groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We draw on data from a representative sample of adults living in Chile conducted in 2015 (n=1,302). We use structural equation models to predict support for police violence for punishment, legal and extra-legal violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Police violence for punishment was strongly related to support for extra-legal punishment. Punitive police violence and extra-legal punishment were both predicted by the motivation to restore status and power relationships, followed by deterrence. In contrast, norm restoration was the main predictor of legal punishment. Police violence for punishment was significantly less supported by ethnic minority members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that police excessive use of force can usefully be understood as police violence as punishment. We discuss the extent to which police repression is perceived to restore status and power hierarchies threatened by crime. We conclude that reducing police violence requires a political and cultural process well beyond reforming police protocols and procedures. Working towards more horizontal relations between police officers, citizens and minority groups should reduce perceived needs to restore power and status relationships, hereby reducing support for police violence as punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acting collectively to confront injustice</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica0/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>System Justification and Perceptions of Group-Based Discrimination. Investigating the Temporal Order of the Ideologically Motivated Minimization (or Exaggeration) of Discrimination Across Low- and High-Status Groups</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20224/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/jb_20224/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Collection With Indigenous People: Fieldwork Experiences From Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At present, the Mapuche are the largest indigenous group living in Chile and, up until the present day, they are considered a disadvantaged group in Chilean society in terms of poverty, education and discrimination indicators. In recent decades, this group has been involved in a violent conflict with the Chilean state, forestry and hydroelectric industries and big landowners due mainly to territorial claims of the ancestral land that is currently inhabited and exploited by these different actors. In the present chapter, we narrate the process of data collection with indigenous participants within the framework of a three-year long project about representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between the Mapuche and the non-indigenous majority in Chile. We focus on the challenges that data collection involved by highlighting the process of participant recruitment and trust issues revolving around data collection, as well as retribution practices. Moreover, we also highlight the pros and cons of having non-indigenous Chilean and international researchers conducting fieldwork in this context. Another aspect we address is how methodological approaches may influence the data quality and participants’ degree of involvement with the project, by highlighting how these issues interconnect with cultural differences and this indigenous group’s worldview and cultural practices. We hope this chapter may provide significant insights on how to deal with some of the difficulties that data collection with indigenous people may involve.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Collectivism and Tightness Moderate Responses to Norm Violators: Effects on Power Perception, Moral Emotions, and Leader Support</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Responses to norm violators are poorly understood. On one hand, norm violators are perceived as powerful, which may help them to get ahead. On the other hand, norm violators evoke moral outrage, which may frustrate their upward social mobility. We addressed this paradox by considering the role of culture. Collectivistic cultures value group harmony and tight cultures value social order. We therefore hypothesized that collectivism and tightness moderate reactions to norm violators. We presented 2,369 participants in 19 countries with a norm violation or a norm adherence scenario. In individualistic cultures, norm violators were considered more powerful than norm abiders and evoked less moral outrage, whereas in collectivistic cultures, norm violators were considered less powerful and evoked more moral outrage. Moreover, respondents in tighter cultures expressed a stronger preference for norm followers as leaders. Cultural values thus influence responses to norm violators, which may have downstream consequences for violators’ hierarchical positions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between indigenous and non-indigenous people: The Mapuche in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Representations of history and present-day intergroup relations between indigenous and non-indigenous people: The Mapuche in Chile&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracing Mapuche Exclusion from Post-Dictatorial Truth Commissions in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This article critically examines the official misrecognition of Mapuche experiences of violence during Augusto Pinochet’s dictatorship (1973–1990) in state-sponsored truth commissions in Chile. We examine official post-dictatorial truth commission politics, narratives and procedures, analyzing how they envisioned the Mapuche as a political (absent) subject and how specific and homogenizing notions of victimhood were produced. We draw attention to three forms of cultural response by the Mapuche toward the official practices of the truth commissions from a bottom-up perspective: indifference, ambivalence and cultural resistance. We then draw attention to unofficial initiatives by nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) and grassroots groups that have aimed to tackle this gap in the transitional justice mechanisms by creating oppositional knowledge. We see in these counter initiatives a valuable knowledge that could allow the creation of bridges between Mapuche communities, mechanisms of transitional justice, grassroots and NGO activism and the Chilean state.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inequality and Capabilities: A Multidimensional Empirical Exploration in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Inequality and Capabilities: A Multidimensional Empirical Exploration in Chile&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the justification of intergroup violence: The roles of procedural justice, police legitimacy, and group identity in attitudes toward violence among indigenous people</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do people justify intergroup violence? We examine public attitudes toward violence perpetrated by indigenous activists to claim for rights and violence by police officers against indigenous people. We assess the roles that group identity, perceived police legitimacy, and procedurally just policing toward indigenous people play in the justification of intergroup violence among members of that minority group. Method: We present findings from 2 surveys (Study 1, n = 1,493; Study 2, n = 198) and an experiment (Study 3, n = 76) conducted among indigenous people in Chile. Studies 1 and 2 measure, and Study 3 manipulates, perceptions of police procedural justice toward indigenous people. Effects of procedural justice on police legitimacy (Studies 2 and 3) and attitudes toward violence for social change and social control (Studies 1–3) are analyzed. Result: Higher perceptions of procedurally just policing toward indigenous people predict higher support for police violence and lower support for violence perpetrated by indigenous activists. These effects are mediated by perceived police legitimacy and moderated by identification with the minority group. Among indigenous people who identify strongly with their group, perceiving high procedural justice predicts greater police legitimacy, greater support for police violence, and lesser support for violence perpetrated by indigenous activists. Conclusions: Findings contribute to an emerging literature on the roles of procedural justice and legitimacy in violence perceptions. They suggest that fair, respectful, and neutral treatment by police officers toward indigenous people may shape people’s views on the appropriateness of various forms of police and civic violence in a particular intergroup context. (PsycInfo Database Record (c) 2020 APA, all rights reserved)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Justifying violence: legitimacy, ideology and public support for police use of force</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under what conditions do people support police use of force? In this paper we assess some of the empirical links between police legitimacy, political ideology (right-wing authoritarianism and social dominance orientation), and support for ‘reasonable’ use of force (e.g. an officer striking a citizen in self-defence) and ‘excessive’ use of force (e.g. an officer using violence to arrest an unarmed person who is not offering violent resistance). Analysing data from an online survey with US participants (n = 186) we find that legitimacy is a positive predictor of reasonable but not excessive police use of force, and that political ideology predicts support for excessive but not reasonable use of force. We conclude with the idea that legitimacy places normative constraints around police power. On the one hand, legitimacy is associated with increased support for the use of force, but only when violence is bounded within certain acceptable limits. On the other hand, excessive use of force seems to require an extra-legal justification that is – at least in our analysis – partly ideological. Our findings open up a new direction of research in what is currently a rather sparse psychological literature on the ability of legitimacy to ‘tame’ coercive power.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>¿Malestar de qué? A propósito de ciertos malentendidos entre malestar social y sufrimiento psíquico en Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/fja-maca4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/fja-maca4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;¿Malestar de qué? A propósito de ciertos malentendidos entre malestar social y sufrimiento psíquico en Chile&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development and validation of a scale of support for violence in the context of intergroup conflict (SVIC): The case of violence perpetrated by Mapuche people and the police in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We develop and validate a scale that measures support for violence in the context of an asymmetrical intergroup conflict between the Chilean state and the largest ethnic minority group in Chile, the Mapuche people: the scale of Support for Violence in an Intergroup Conflict (SVIC). The proposed scale has two dimensions that capture the perceived acceptability of violence carried out in both directions: support for violence carried out by radical Mapuche activists and support for violence carried out by the police in the name of the Chilean state. We validate the scale in a survey conducted using two independent samples: a sample of Mapuche (n1=199) and a sample of non-indigenous Chilean respondents (n2=195). We test measurement invariance of the scale and find evidence that it is a valid instrument across both samples. Furthermore, findings suggest that the scale has discriminant validity, i.e., it correlates weakly with aggressiveness; as well as convergent validity, i.e., support for violence carried out by Mapuche activists correlates positively with Mapuche identification and negatively with Chilean identification, and the reverse is true for support for violence carried out by the police. We finish by highlighting the importance of measuring support for violence in the context of an asymmetrical intergroup conflict considering violence carried out by the different parties involved in the conflict, as well as the importance of validating the scale considering samples of representatives of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Authority and Punishment: On the Ideological Basis of Punitive Attitudes towards Criminals</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three explanations dominate the literature as to why people support tough sentencing of criminal offenders. The first is an instrumental perspective: people are concerned about becoming a victim of crime and they look to punishment to reduce future harm. The second is a relational perspective: people are concerned about community breakdown, and they support punishment to restore moral boundaries. The third is a psychological model based on ideological preferences: people desire conformity and authority in society, and they look to institutions to punish transgressions that threaten collective security. Building on the work of Tyler and Boeckmann (1977), we show that right-wing authoritarianism predicts both the extent to which people worry about social threats and the extent to which they support harsh punitive measures. Bridging research from political psychology and criminology, we conclude with the idea that popular punitive sentiment is grounded in an uncritical submission to authorities, an adherence to conservative moral values, and consonant concerns about collective security and cohesion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Los tiempos de la Politización. Informe de Desarrollo Humano 2015</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Los tiempos de la Politización. Informe de Desarrollo Humano 2015&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Perspectives and Subjective Wellbeing in Chile</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The present article aims to provide evidence to advance in the comprehension of the multiple relationships between temporality and wellbeing by exploring the relationship between time perspectives and subjective wellbeing in Chile. In so doing, it presents a critical stand of the current operationalisations of the ‘balanced time perspective’ (BTP). This article supports the theoretical premise that individuals’ time perspectives possess a contextual nature and that the BTP is socially relative. As a result, the article proposes a novel method to define and operationalise BTP. Using data from the United Nations Development Programme’s 2011 Human Development Survey for Chile (N = 2,535), an empirical analysis is carried out on the relationship between time perspectives and vital satisfaction, positive affects, negative affects and depressive symptomatology scales. The results show that in Chile a negative orientation towards the past exerts the most significant effect on subjective wellbeing and malaise, and the time perspective which most favours subjective wellbeing in Chilean society is that in which there is a low orientation towards Present and Past-Negative, a high orientation towards Past-Positive, and a medium orientation towards Future. This relationship between time perspectives and subjective wellbeing constitutes an advance in the study of the subjective dimension of temporality in Chile, and contributes to the theoretical and methodological discussions on time perspectives on an international level.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Control Social y Justificación de la Violencia en Chile. Resultados Encuesta Nacional UDP 2015</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ac-monica/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ac-monica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Too long to compensate? Time perceptions, emotions, and compensation for colonial conflicts</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-ana4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the present article we analyze the role of perceptions of time and ingroup-focused compunction and anger on the desire to compensate the outgroup in relation to historical colonial conflicts. Furthermore, we analyze the relationships between the aforementioned variables and perceptions of the past as being violent and perceptions that compensation has been enough. By means of multiple group structural equation modeling using 1 Portuguese sample (N = 170) and 1 Dutch sample (N = 238), we were able to show that perceptions of the time passed between the negative events and the present day are negatively related to compensatory behavioral intentions. Furthermore, the belief that past compensation has been enough is negatively related to ingroup-focused anger and compunction. Anger (Portuguese sample only) and compunction are positively associated with intentions of compensation. The implications of our results for the field of intergroup relations are discussed. (PsycINFO Database Record (c) 2016 APA, all rights reserved)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retribution as Revenge and Retribution as Just Deserts</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica8/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Riesgos psicosociales laborales, características organizacionales y salud mental: {El} rol mediador de la violencia laboral</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica9/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La exposición a riesgos psicosociales y violencia laboral se asocia con una mayor presencia de problemas de salud mental en los/as trabajadores/as. El presente estudio tuvo como objetivo indagar el rol mediador de la violencia laboral entre los riesgos psicosociales (ISOSTRAIN, desbalance esfuerzo-recompensa), antecedentes organizacionales (liderazgo tiránico) y problemas de salud mental (distrés) en 1023 trabajadores/as de tres hospitales públicos chilenos de alta complejidad de tres regiones del país. Se hipotetizó que la exposición a riesgos psicosociales y algunas características organizacionales (liderazgo tiránico) se asocia a menores niveles de salud mental y que parte de este efecto se encuentra mediado por la exposición a violencia laboral. Se aplicó un cuestionario incluyendo el Negative Act Questionnaire Revised (NAQ-R), el Screening de Distrés Psicológico, la Escala de Liderazgo Destructivo, el Cuestionario de Desbalance Esfuerzo-Recompensa y el Job Content Questionnaire. Mediante análisis de senderos, se observó que la exposición a riesgos psicosociales, liderazgo tiránico y violencia laboral aumenta los niveles de distrés de los/as trabajadores/as. Parte del efecto de los riesgos psicosociales y el liderazgo tiránico en la salud mental se encuentra mediado por la exposición a violencia laboral. El artículo termina discutiendo la necesidad de avanzar en protocolos y prevención de riesgos psicosociales y violencia laboral, en particular en el contexto del trabajo en salud pública.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Identities and Conflict in Chile: The Role of Historical and Political Processes</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, we seek to integrate historical and contextual perspectives with socio-psychological theories to better understand the development of social identities and conflicts in Chile. Specifically, we analyse across different contexts, ethnic identity, national identity in the context of immigration, political, gender and social class identities. We address the historical background that gave rise to status and power differences, the nature of these intergroup relations and the conflicts associated with the groups involved. We conclude by arguing that in order for a modern society to tackle the challenges imposed by multiculturalism and social diversity, historical and political processes need to be considered, in addition to the needs of belonging, distinctiveness and factors that might threaten social identities. Fostering opportunities to experience positive intergroup encounters, in which, groups can learn from each other and more importantly, can live in peace without feeling threatened by the presence of other groups is seen as crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public Opinion Towards the Lay Magistracy and the Sentencing Council Guidelines: The Effects of Information on Attitudes</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-monica6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public opinion surveys have long documented public criticism of ‘lenient’ sentencers. There are two principal perceptions contributing to negative attitudes: a lack of community input and the view that sentencers determine sentence according to their own views. This study embeds an experimental design within a representative survey of respondents in England and Wales (n = 1,004), supplemented by laboratory-based work (n = 230) and focus groups. Results demonstrated that the public is ill-informed about both the magistracy and the sentencing guidelines. In addition, providing information about sentencing changed public attitudes to sentencing and reduced public punitiveness. Respondents were less critical of disposals and less punitive in their own sentence recommendations when they had been given context about the structure of sentencing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bienestar Subjetivo: El Desafío De Repensar El Desarrollo</title>
      <link>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca5/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>www.oles.cl/publication/ja-maca5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spanish Abstract: Hoy está en marcha una conversación pública global relativa al desarrollo. Diversos actores plantean cada vez más la necesidad de poner atención a otras dimensiones además del crecimiento económico (o del modo tradicional de concebirlo), lo cual implica afinar los objetivos, los puntos de llegada, el horizonte normativo, incluso las mediciones estadísticas; obliga a asumir en la acción pública aquello que “importa en última instancia” cuando se aspira al desarrollo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
